Hello everyone and welcome back to English
Pod. My name is Marco and my name is
Catherine and it is the holiday season
that means we're talking about Christmas
and Christmas shopping. We've got a great
lesson for you today. Exactly so we're
going to be looking for a Christmas
gift and so let's listen to our dialogue
for the first time and we'll
be back to explain some words.
Bill, Bill, you got to help me. What's
wrong? Slow down. You're going to give
yourself a heart attack. Tomorrow's
Christmas and I haven't bought my mom
anything I'm such a bad son. Take it easy.
Let's go to the mall, window shop a little
and see if there's anything she might like.
That's just it. I don't know what to
get her. Last year I got her a ring
that was two sizes too big and a pair of
shoes five sizes too small. I suck at
getting presents for people. That's
where you're making a big mistake. You
can't just guess people's likes or sizes
especially with clothes or jewelry.
On top of that I think that you should get
your mom something that shows how much
you love her. At the same time you should
show her that you took the time and
effort to look for something that she would
really like. Yeah you're right. When it
comes down to it I can be pretty tacky.
Yeah, tell me about it. I know. Your
mom is trying to learn Spanish right?
Why don't you get her a
gift certificate for this great
website I saw called Spanish
pot? Now that's a great idea.
All right we're back so now why don't
we take a look at language takeaway.
Okay so there are a lot of interesting
words in this dialogue. Some of them
have to do with Christmas and some of
them have to do with shopping. So this
first one has to do with neither actually
phrase. It's a medical term. Right.
He talked about a heart attack. Okay
so you know what a heart is but a heart
attack is when there's no more blood
going into your heart and your heart stops
beating. Okay. It's a very very dangerous
situation. So the person actually said
this because the other guy was like
you gotta help me. He was all very excited.
He was like whoa whoa you know
slow down or you're gonna give yourself
a heart attack. So it's not literal. Yeah
it's not a real heart attack. He's saying
calm down. Calm down. Okay. All right
and well he was very upset because he
hadn't bought a gift and he said I
suck at getting presents for people. I suck
at getting presents for people. Well suck
is not a very polite word my mom used to
get angry at me when I used it but
it's a way to say that I'm very very bad at
doing something. Okay so I suck at playing
tennis. All right because I suck at math.
All right but again this is not
something you should use on a test or an
essay because it's very spoken
colloquial English. Right exactly and this
other word is actually okay to use
and when you're talking about present or
you're talking about decorations you
say something is tacky. Okay well if you
call something tacky this is an adjective
so something is tacky. It's really a
matter of opinion. Right. Okay so I think
this is tacky but you don't maybe that's a
problem. So let me give you an example
of tacky. I think that that clothing with
lots of bows and glitter and shiny
things are very tacky. Okay so it's
something that you don't really like
or you think that is a little bit strange.
That's right. So as you say it's an
opinion because you think that clothes with
bows and teddy bears on it is tacky.
Well somebody else can think no it's cute.
It's nice. Exactly you know you can
also and you can also describe things that
people do as being tacky. So for example
he gave me a present but he left the
price on it. Oh that is. That's so tacky.
Right that is tacky. All right so the
word is tacky and moving on we talked
about a gift certificate. You should get
your mom a gift certificate. Well a
gift certificate is a very popular form of
gift giving now. You know what a gift
is but a certificate is a piece of paper.
Okay so you could have a birth
certificate for example it says when you
were born where you were born but
in this case a gift certificate is a piece
of paper that you give someone to say
you have this much money to spend at
this store. So I could give my mom
a gift certificate for a book store for
$50 and she can go with this piece of
paper and spend $50 for free. Okay because
I already paid. Yeah so it's kind of a very
popular thing to do because sometimes
as in the dialogue you don't know the
person's size or you don't know if they
like this color. So you're just like look
here is you know a gift certificate for
$100 go to the store that I know you
really like and get yourself whatever you
want something nice. Exactly. But it's less
tacky than giving that person cash right.
Right cash is considered a tacky gift.
Yeah. I'm not really sure why it just did
it's a social custom but very popular
right now are these gift certificates
or even gift cards they look like credit
cards. Very good. All right so why don't
we listen to our dialogue again and
we'll return shortly to take a look at
Fluency Builder. Bill Bill you got to
help me what's wrong slow down you're
going to give yourself a heart attack.
Tomorrow's Christmas and I haven't
bought my mom anything I'm such a bad son.
Take it easy let's go to the mall
window shop a little and see if there's
anything she might like. That's just
it. I don't know what to get her.
Last year I got her a ring that was two
sizes too big and a pair of shoes
five sizes too small. I suck at getting
presents for people. That's where
you're making a big mistake. You can't just
guess people's likes or sizes especially
with clothes or jewelry. On top of
that I think that you should get your
mom something that shows how much you
love her. At the same time you should
show her that you took the time and
effort to look for something that
she would really like. Yeah you're right.
When it comes down to it I can be pretty
tacky. Yeah tell me about it. I know your
mom is trying to learn Spanish right?
Why don't you get her a gift certificate
for this great website I saw called
Spanish Pod. Now that's a great idea.
All right we're back so now why don't
we take a look at four key phrases on
Fluency Builder. Fluency Builder. Okay
I like this first phrase sometimes I have
to use it about other people. Sometimes
people use it on me. You say take it easy.
Take it easy. Take it easy relax.
Yeah this is a way to say hey become.
So there's no you don't you can't really
translate it right. We'll take what easy.
You can't but this is third two main
context. Okay there are two situations
where this is really popular. One is this.
Oh my god Marco. Oh my god I'm freaking
out. I really need your help on this
and I really need you to just really
just be involved. Take it easy
all right relax. Take it easy.
All right so that's someone who's
upset and you're tying them to calm down.
The second situation is when you're saying
goodbye to someone this is a very kind of
against spoken language. A comfortable
way of saying hey see you later.
Right so I was like all right bye take it
easy. Yeah take it easy have a good one.
Yeah have a good one isn't it? Yeah take
it easy that means that means take the life
easy don't rush don't rush. Yeah
enjoy your life. So if you try this with
your your English speaking friends you're
saying goodbye you say hey take it easy.
Yeah bye take it easy. It's a nice
one. Very nice. All right and our second
phrase is actually it's interesting
because when he talked about the ring
that he got for her mom that was
two sizes too big and if pair of shoes five
sizes too small. So the construction there
two sizes too big five sizes too small.
This is a very important construction
and it doesn't quite make sense
when you hear it so that's what we're
gonna explain right now. Let me try to
explain this using an example. Okay if I
have a size seven shoe and my brother
gives me a Christmas present of size
nine shoes I say Peter these shoes are two
sizes too big okay that's the number
two two sizes TOO too big that means
they're too big for me by two sizes
because the difference between seven and
nine is two. Right but if it gives me a
size five shoe say Peter these shoes are
two sizes too small. That means that you
know five is two less than seven. So this
is a very popular construction. So
you're saying specifically how much bigger
or how much smaller the shoes are in
the case with the ring or shoes or anything
that has a size. Exactly but the funny
thing is you can also exaggerate you
could say oh this sweater is so ugly
it's ten sizes too big for me it's not
really expensive. Right so but you
can use this construction right using one
size too big etc even when you're
buying something to the store to the lady
in the store you can say I think the
shoe is a two sizes too big can you give
me a smaller pair. Exactly all right
and our third phrase for today when the
person said yeah you're right when it
comes down to it I can be pretty tacky so
we looked at tacky but what does he
mean when it comes down to it. Okay well
this it is very confusing sometimes
when we talk about phrases in English but
when it comes down to it is way to say
in reality or actually or the truth is yes.
So it's a way to say something is
truthful. Okay so I can say when it comes
down to it Catherine is a good friend.
All right so when times are tough or in
the end or actually maybe you have your
small faults but you are a good friend.
Right or when it comes down to it
Marco is a really hard worker so sometimes
he likes to play video games but
when it's a really important he will work
really hard. Very good so very good
uses of this phrase and you can use it in
many different contexts and for our
fourth phrase when the person said yeah
tell me about it. What does it mean tell
me about it tell me about what. Okay well
this is a really very popular phrase
you hear this all the time and it's it's a
way to say yeah I agree I understand I
understand so this is this is a phrase that
means agreement okay so I can say God
I really hate winter because when I leave
work it's always really dark yeah
tell me about it it's always dark and it
makes me feel lazy. Right and so Marco
is agreeing he says I don't like it either
yeah so this is a very very spoken way
spoken language way of agreeing with
someone's he say yeah tell me about it.
Right so it's a it's very natural it's
a very natural way of agreeing with
someone right. Exactly. All right so great
phrases why don't we take
a look at our dialogue for the
last time and we'll be
back to talk a little bit more.
Bill Bill you got to help me. What's wrong
slow down you're gonna give yourself a
heart attack. Tomorrow's Christmas
and I haven't bought my mom anything I'm
such a bad son. Take it easy let's go
to the mall window shop a little and see
if there's anything she might like. That's
just it. I don't know what to get her.
Last year I got her a ring that was
two sizes too big and a pair of shoes five
sizes too small. I suck at getting
presents for people. That's where you're
making a big mistake. You can't just
guess people's likes or sizes especially
with clothes or jewelry. On top of that
I think that you should get your mom
something that shows how much you love her.
At the same time you should show
her that you took the time and effort
to look for something that she would
really like. Yeah you're right. When it
comes down to it I can be pretty tacky.
Yeah tell me about it. I know your
mom is trying to learn Spanish right.
Why don't you get her a
gift certificate for this great
website I saw called Spanish
Pod. Now that's a great idea.
All right great so now that the crisp.
All right so as we said gift certificates
are a good idea but you know what else
do you like to give as Christmas presents?
Personally I like things that people
really think about and spend their
time doing or making. So I like for
example my mom is a beautiful quilter.
She makes these big blankets and quilts
them and sometimes she even quilts names
and stuff and so those are really wonderful
gifts because they're you know the
person thinks about you and who you
are and what you want and so I like to be
able to give gifts like that but I'm not
necessarily that creative so you know I
think it's nice to give to give gifts like
tickets to a music show or things like
that where you know the person will go
and have a good time and enjoy themselves.
Yeah I think that's really important
because sometimes people just give gifts
because you have to but stuff. Yeah
like stuff and you're like oh great you
know a tie. It's like kind of impersonal.
At the same time you know if you're
if you're dad or your boyfriend or
somebody is a it loves ties and has a 50 of
them and you get them another one that's
really interesting or unique then great
you know but it is good to take the time
to get somebody something they really
like or they would really use or enjoy.
Exactly. So what kind of gifts do you
plan to give this holiday season? Do you
celebrate Christmas? Let us know on our
website EnglishPod.com. Right we'll see
you guys there and until next time. Bye!